<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Joel McMurry</title>
    <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Joel McMurry</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>jmp</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/jmp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/jmp/</guid>
      <description>Child Care Policy and Informal Care Draft
Early child care experiences vary widely across the distribution of socio-economic status (SES), and sizeable skill gaps open up before children enter publicly-provided schooling. SES gradients in the quality of informal, relative-provided, care are particularly large. To understand how variation in the availability and quality of informal care contributes to skill inequality, I estimate a model of child care, mother labor supply, and child skill development, allowing for unequal access to informal care. I exploit the timing of grandmother deaths relative to a child’s birth to identify substitution patterns between informal, formal, and mother-provided child care. I quantify the effect of having access to informal care on child development and mother labor supply, and I estimate that, for a substantial fraction of less-advantaged children, the availability of informal care is detrimental to skill development. I ex ante analyze the effects of policies such as universal public daycare, subsidies for formal care, and cash transfers, and show that accounting for heterogeneity in the availability and quality of informal care is quantitatively important for estimating the effect that such policies might have on skill inequality at the point of entry into K-12 schooling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Summer Matter</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/making_summer_matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/making_summer_matter/</guid>
      <description>Making Summer Matter: The Impact of Youth Employment on Academic Performance Quantitative Economics (2021) with Amy Ellen Schwartz, Jacob Leos-Urbel, and Matthew Wiswall Paper Supplement
This paper examines New York City&amp;rsquo;s Summer Youth Employment Program (SYEP). SYEP provides jobs to youth ages 14-24, and due to high demand for summer jobs, allocates slots through a random lottery system. We match student-level data from the SYEP program with educational records from the NYC Department of Education and use the random lottery to estimate the effects of SYEP participation on a number of academic outcomes, including test taking and performance. We find that SYEP participation has positive impacts on student academic outcomes, and these effects are particularly large for students who participate in SYEP multiple times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CCQQ</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/childcare_quantity_quality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/childcare_quantity_quality/</guid>
      <description>Inequality in Early Care Experienced by U.S. Children with Sarah Flood, Aaron Sojourner, and Matthew Wiswall NBER Working Paper No. 29249
Using every major nationally-representative dataset on parental and non-parental care provided to children up to age 6, we quantify differences in American children’s care experiences by socioeconomic status (SES), proxied primarily with maternal education. Increasingly, higher-SES children spend less time with their parents and more time in the care of others. Non-parental care for high-SES children is more likely to be in childcare centers, where average quality is higher, and less likely to be provided by relatives where average quality is lower. Even within types of childcare, higher-SES children tend to receive care of higher measured quality and higher cost. Inequality is evident at home as well: measures of parental enrichment at home, from both self-reports and outside observers, are on average higher for higher-SES children. We also find that parental and non-parental quality is reinforcing: children who receive higher quality non-parental care also tend to receive higher quality parental care.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Child Health Production</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/child_health_production/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/child_health_production/</guid>
      <description>On the Production of Health in Children with Naoki Aizawa and Matthew Wiswall </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Family Risk</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/family_risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/family_risk/</guid>
      <description>Risk-Taking, Family Resources, and a Fuller View of the Portfolio with Annika Bacher and Eirik Brandsaas </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Skills, Savings, and the Family</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/skills_savings_family/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/skills_savings_family/</guid>
      <description>Skills, Savings, and the Family Draft (Coming Soon)
I consider how intra-family insurance between prime-age adults and their elderly parents affects incentives to invest in the human capital of children. I document gradients in skills and measures of investment in child human capital with respect to grandparent wealth and health, even accounting for parent resources. Interpreting this as suggesting evidence that grandparent resources shift savings and investment incentives for parents, I jointly model the production of child skills and the consumption-savings of parents and grandparents in an environment with income, health, and expenditure risk and altruistic links but no commitment. I show that such a model provides sharp predictions regarding the importance of intra-family insurance relative to bequests in shifting parental incentives across the lifecycle. A calibrated version of the model is able to qualitatively reproduce the investment gradients present in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intergen Portfolio Choice</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/intergen_portchoice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/intergen_portchoice/</guid>
      <description>Intra-family Insurance, Portfolio Choice, and Inter-generational Wealth Inequality with Eirik Brandsaas Draft (Coming Soon)
We consider how intra-family insurance affects household portfolio choices and savings decisions. Empirically, we find that stock market participation and the fraction of assets invested in stocks are increasing in measures of family member human capital. Taking this as suggestive evidence that intra-family insurance reduces risk aversion, we study a model of consumption, savings, and portfolio choice with two-sided altruism and no commitment in which parents and children can insure each other. In the model, agents with family members of lower human capital optimally choose to hold lower portfolio weights, reducing the average rate of return obtained. Families with lower human capital thus not only have lower labor income, but also lower rates of return, potentially propagating both the level and persistence in wealth inequality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Capital and College Prospects</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/hc_college_prospects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/hc_college_prospects/</guid>
      <description>Human Capital and College Prospects This paper studies how parental investment in the human capital of children responds to changes in the college environment the child will face in late adolescence. I develop and estimate a dynamic model of parental savings and investment in which parents make a trade-off between saving in financial assets or the human capital of their child. Parents care about their asset position at the end of the finite decision problem as well as the quality of college their child enjoys. College quality is produced by combining tuition dollars, a choice made by the parent, and the human capital of the child in the terminal period. These inputs are complementary, so policies that increase tuition spending on the child will increase the return to investing in one&amp;rsquo;s child during childhood. I simulate three counterfactual education policies: an unconditional transfer, a conditional tuition grant, and a policy that approximates free public university.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marijuana</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/marijuana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/marijuana/</guid>
      <description>The Effect of Cannabis Legalization on the Frequency of Hospitalizations for Cannabis Hyperemesis Syndrome with Isabel Hujoel and Joseph Murray </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>State-Level Capital</title>
      <link>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/state_level_capital/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://joelmcmurry.github.io/research/state_level_capital/</guid>
      <description>Capital and Productivity in US States with Noah Williams We study United States economic growth at the state level over the period from 1970-2015. Our main contribution is the construction of new data series on capital at the state and industry level, using data on the aggregate capital stock and payments to capital at the state and industry level. We use published data and neoclassical theory to construct this data, as there are no official data on investment or capital at the state level. We use this data to study capital accumulation and convergence across states, as well as levels and trends in factor shares across states, regions, and industries. We show that the decline in labor&amp;rsquo;s share of income was strongest in states where it was initially the highest, and while labor&amp;rsquo;s share fell in manufacturing it increased in services. Thus even as manufacturing shrank and services grew as a share of total output, labor&amp;rsquo;s share declined overall.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>